Hello and welcome to the Telescope.
Every week we bring you a fresh insight from
the biggest car market in the world.
Now, in the previous video,
I have explained why I stopped reviewing
XPeng products for a while in the GX review.
But this MONA L03 is going to be the restart
button of my XPeng reviews.
Because this car is so well done, so well
finished,
that I would go as far as saying XPeng is
now a sub-brand of MONA.
This is a very coherent and, dare I say,
original design.
I know some people will moan that the
headlight looks like a Polestar's.
A Polestar is now struggling for its
existence,
while this is going to be delivering at more
than 20,000 units per month in China.
So for most people in the world,
this is actually the more familiar headlight
design.
Everything, every line on this car just
makes total sense.
On size, this is one size below Model Y, but
it's still on 20-inch wheels.
This is an option, and I do think it's worth
it.
Also, I need to point out,
you only get Goodyear tyres on this 20-inch
optional package.
The front wheel arch and the rear wheel arch
both feel very powerful,
and a small tip at the back.
This is a very coherent design.
I cannot imagine this is from the same brand
that designed the horrendous GX.
Here on the inside, this L03 is very
comfortable just being itself,
being a 140,000 RMB car.
By that, I mean, unlike the XPeng GX, which
is a 270,000 RMB car,
but that car's interior is pretending to be
a 400,000 RMB car and failed miserably.
This interior is plain and simple.
Dare I say, in some areas, too simple,
but you could forgive it because of the
price point.
And also, if you like a Tesla,
then you will like this because it doesn't
have anything it doesn't need to have.
All of the materials make sense at this
price point.
This is a very honest car — and I'm going to
repeat that word — a very coherent and
comfortable car with its own identity.
This car has been launched in Europe
simultaneously,
and I can tell a bit of European influence
because I often say the huge adjustment
range of the steering wheel.
Well, this is not just huge by Chinese car
standard.
This is huge by European car standard.
A lot of people, whether you are six foot
four or very, very short female,
anyone can easily find a very comfortable
driving position in this.
That's the first impact.
Secondly, this car has an unusually good
rear visibility for a coupe SUV.
It's still a bit of a letterbox,
but I will say this gives you triple the
amount of rear visibility coverage compared
to a Tesla Model Y.
I know that's a really low benchmark to
compare against,
but I can sense XPeng has spent some effort
trying to optimize the rear visibility
of this.
Secondly, this car's central headrest
matches with the bottom of the rear screen,
which means this central headrest is not in
the way.
This is unlike the Lynk & Co 07 GT I showed
you recently,
which is completely in the way.
I can clearly see the engineering and
ergonomics
team spend some effort to optimize
the rear visibility of a coupe SUV like
this.
And that is very, very rare in the Chinese
car market.
I'm now recovering from the zero-gravity
available passenger seat.
It's in an option package, which I think
everyone should take.
I do hope the driver's seat could also have
zero-gravity seats,
because if I want to have this kind of
experience and I'm using the car alone,
let's say I'm charging the car,
I do wish the front passenger seat in the
next model year update could also have
zero-gravity mode.
One complaint I have with the infotainment
is all of the fonts are too small.
And this is coming from someone who uses the
smallest font on my iPhone.
So if this is small for me, then it's too
small for just about everyone.
You can choose to enlarge the font in the
HUD and also, I believe,
enlarge the fonts in the infotainment.
But now all of the font sizes make sense,
but all of the icons are still too small for
the drivers and the passengers sitting
at their normal position to view.
This looks good on the design screen of that
UI designer,
but it doesn't quite make sense here in the
car.
Here in the rear,
the only piece of criticism I can provide is
that this car does not have a sun blind.
But given the price point, I can sort of
forgive it.
Everything else makes total sense.
The front is set to my position.
I can very easily tuck my feet into the
bottom of the front seat.
The space is fine.
The seat back angle makes sense.
The seat cushion is supportive while not
being too harsh.
The central armrest is big.
I mean, I believe this car is more than 20
centimetres shorter than a Model Y.
This is clearly a class smaller than the
Model Y.
But this actually has a much better rear
cabin than a Model Y could ever dream for.
And this is also much cheaper than a Model
Y,
depending on where you are purchasing this
from.
In China this is a 140,000 RMB car. I'll put
its price in Europe on screen.
Yeah, this is an unusually good rear cabin
for its price.
Boot is on the smaller side.
It's from this that you can tell this is a
Chinese car.
I would say this is barely any bigger than
the standard European hatchback.
You do have a little bit of underfloor
storage,
but it's nothing to write home about.
This is the pure electric version, so it
doesn't have an engine.
Therefore, you have roughly a 100-litre-ish
frunk.
But the opening of this frunk is so deep
into the nose and it's facing the sky.
You know, taking things in and out of this
frunk is not easy at all.
You can very easily scratch some paint when
you are offloading and loading stuff
into this.
So much so that I don't think many people
will actually use this unless you are in a
pinch where the boot is totally full and you
have to use this.
This is one area where I think Onvo's
Qinling will have an advantage over this if
you don't know what that car is.
It's basically Onvo's MONA,
Onvo's more budget-friendly line that's
supposed to come out roughly next year.
This is one area where I think the Qinling
will have the advantage.
And from this, you can tell this is a
Chinese car.
It focused more towards the rear cabin.
But another thing I just noticed is that
this car's boot opening button,
it's also downward facing.
If you watch my recent review of the SAIC
Volkswagen 5S,
I said that car's boot opening button is
very difficult to find.
This is also downward facing, but it's not
difficult to find at all.
First of all, it's completely central.
It's on the centre line of the button.
And even if I stand very close to it, it
sticks out a little bit.
So I can very easily operate it blind.
I found this boot opening button on the
first try.
I'm just saying this car, a lot of the
ergonomics, usability, ease of use,
is clearly optimized for the European car
market.
This car has unusually good ergonomics for
an XPeng.
Dynamically, because you can individualize
your driving mode,
if you set steering to heavy,
power to sport and brake pedal feel to sport
and suspension to comfort,
that's my preferred setting, then this is a
very accomplished, dynamically,
very polished car.
You can tell the 20-inch wheel, the optional
20-inch wheel,
has some structural noise.
That's kind of inevitable when you fit
wheels this big onto a car this small,
and also it's running 45-section tyres.
But I wouldn't say it's horrendous,
and considering how much better looking this
20-inch wheel is compared to the
18-inch, I'll still suggest people to choose
the 20-inch wheel.
And also, you only get the Goodyear tyre,
which is so important.
I mean, don't choose budget tyres.
It's the single most important component
that
can provide the most noticeable upgrade.
That is the tyre.
It's the only contact patch your car has
with the road.
And yeah, just because of that Goodyear
tyre, it's worth it.
The car we have here today is the Ultra SE
spec,
which is the top spec of the MONA L03,
which has the dual Turing ADAS chip that is
XPeng's in-house ADAS chip.
I do wonder how many people will choose this
spec,
because this car has about 100 GB of memory
crammed in — for a car this cheap.
And also, if you're watching this video two
or three years later,
you wouldn't understand how expensive video
memory is in September 2026.
I think most people will be better off
choosing the single Turing,
which is the Max spec of this car.
All of these things I'm talking about only
applies to China.
For Europe, this is a totally different
conversation.
For the single Turing setup, XPeng has just
released the VLA 2.0 ADAS model.
That is the distilled model,
a smaller size model compared to the dual
Turing setup that we have here today.
I do think that version is more appropriate
for this car's price point.
I don't think many people will choose the
dual Turing setup of this car.
But still, it takes nothing away from this
car's ADAS performance.
This has the ADAS performance that other
cars
at this price range could only dream of.
This is top-tier performance — probably only
below FSD Beta and Huawei's ADS 5.0
here in China.
But this is a 140,000 RMB car.
One other thing I have to say is this car's
design is so fantastic.
You are conscious of this car's powerful
design while you are sitting in the
driver's seat.
I mean, I'll just show you.
This is the view I'm getting looking
forward.
The front wheel arch is so powerfully in my
vision.
And also, if I look in the mirror, both
sides,
I can see the very powerful rear haunches.
I mean, this is a very budget friendly coupe
SUV.
And it's giving me kind of a sports car vibe
to this.
One other criticism I have with this car is
its one-pedal driving mode.
You can choose to turn this on in the
infotainment.
However, that final bit of braking, just
before standstill,
is not up there with Tesla.
I'll just quickly demonstrate.
We are sitting at a standstill.
I'll press the brake, press the throttle.
Six, five…
I don't know if you can tell.
There's a bit of a bouncing back, rearward
motion after coming to a standstill,
which is not there on the Tesla.
It's very, very subtle.
I'm not sure whether you can feel what I'm
telling you.
Watch my head and neck movement.
The car has a tendency to move backwards
after it has come to a standstill,
which means that final bit of braking is not
up there with Tesla.
On the plus side,
you can choose to have different levels of
regen with your one-pedal driving mode,
which is a trick that so many other brands
missed.
This is one of the few Chinese brands with a
one-pedal driving mode where you can
choose different levels of regen.
But still, that final bit of braking, you
still need to spend some effort on it.
BYD and Geely are both looking at this
scratching their heads because they cannot
match this.
BYD doesn't have the taste for this design.
Having said that, I cannot believe I'm
talking about taste on an XPeng,
having just spent a whole video criticizing
the lack of taste on the XPeng GX.
But this is the reality.
The much cheaper MONA L03 has much better
taste than the range-topping GX.
Neither BYD nor Geely has anything like the
ADAS performance and also the
infotainment design on this.
This is, as of now, early September 2026.
This is the best compact electric SUV in the
world.
That is all from the Telescope today.
If you enjoyed this video, keep watching,
keep subscribing.
More videos coming along very soon.